اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ۝
بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرًا
During the advances of the army of Khalid Ibn Walid رضي الله عنه
we talked about his defeat of Tulaiha Al-Asdi(طليحة ألأسدي).
Saj'jah(سجَّاح) was a woman from the tribe of Taghlub(تغلُب) they were Christians.
She claimed to be a prophet and she came down from Iraq
and a huge number of followers were surrounding her.
So she came in, joined hands with Tulaiha Al-Asdi(طليحة ألأسدي)
and with Musailimah Al-Kazzab(مسيلمة ألكذاب) also
and among the people who made a deal with her.
And again, these were political alliances more than they were religious convictions,
was Malik Bin Nuwairah(مالك بن نويرة).
Malik Bin Nuwairah(مالك بن نويرة) was a Muslim but he refused to pay Zaka'at(زكوة).
And when Saj'jah(سجَّاح) came he made an agreement, a coalition with her.
Now when Tulaiha Al-Asdi(طليحة ألأسدي) was defeated
Saj'jah(سجَّاح) just withdrew, to protect herself.
So, Malik Bin Nuwairah(مالك بن نويرة) was now regretting, what he did, he made the wrong move.
He made the deal with this Saj'jah(سجَّاح), false prophet and now he's left alone
and Khalid Ibn Walid رضي الله عنه was around the corner.
Khalid Ibn Walid رضي الله عنه decided to attack Malik Bin Nuwairah(مالك بن نويرة),
the Ansaar(أنْصَار) told him: We have done what the Siddique(صديق) told us
and we're not going to join you, so he went ahead,
later on the Ansaar(أنْصَار) said:
He's the Ameer(أمير), let's just follow him.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد), his argument was
I cannot wait to get permission from the Khalifah(خليفه)
because this is an opportunity that if I Miss, I'm not going to get again.
I have to pounce on demand now, otherwise it will be too late.
So Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) decided to move ahead
the Ansaar(أنْصَار) reluctantly agreed and they joined him
and they attacked, they ambushed Malik Bin Nuwairah(مالك بن نويرة) and his people.
There are two versions of what happened,
One version is that Khalid Ibn Walid رضي الله عنه captured Malik Bin Nuwairah(مالك بن نويرة)
and discussed the issue of Zaka'at(زكوة) with him and Malik Bin Nuwairah(مالك بن نويرة) said:
I will pray but I'm not going to pay Zaka'at(زكوة).
So Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) ordered his execution.
The other version is that, they were captured and Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) said;
دَّفِّعُوهُم
Give them warmth because it was a very cold night.
And the Arabs had different dialects
I mean it's not that the Arabs in the time of Rasool Allah ﷺ all, have the same dialect,
their dialects were different.
And دَّفِّعُوهُم was understood to mean "Kill Them".
So they were executed whichever version was the more accurate one.
Anyway, after that Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) married the wife of Malik Bin Nuwairah(مالك بن نويرة).
There's a lot of talk that has went around because of the marriage of Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) to the wife of Malik(مالك)
and to the killing of Malik(مالك).
Abu Qatada Al-Ansari(أبوقتادةألأنصاري), he immediately just left
and he went to Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) and he said;
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) has killed the man
whom I witnessed with my own eyes, making the Adhan(آذَان) and praying,
that his people were making the Adhan(آذَان) and praying and then he takes over his wife.
So this was reported to the Khalifah(خليفه).
And it’s an incident that's mentioned in At-Tabri(ألطبري) and in the history books.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه was very angry at this.
And he told Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه that Khalid(خالد) must be fired.
Now again, there's two versions on what happened later
did Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) called Khalid(خالد) or he just sent him a letter.
One version which is mentioned by Ibn Kathir(اِبْنِ كَثِيْر) and At-Tabri(ألطبري) that
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) has called Khalid(خالد) to come to Madina, so that he can investigate the matter.
So Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) comes in to the Masjid An-Nabwi(مسجدألنبوي)
in his chainmail which is rusty because of the blood that has accumulated on it
and he's wearing his turban and sticking out of it, arrows.
And he comes in to the Masjid An-Nabwi(مسجدألنبوي).
So Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) when he sees him, he jumps at him.
He grabs him and he pulls out the arrows from his turban and he says;
You have committed hypocrisy by killing a Muslim and then you take over his wife.
Khalid Ibn Walid رضي الله عنه did not answer back, he was silent and did not say anything.
Because he thought that maybe this is the view of the Khalifah(خليفه) too and I'm in trouble
so he just stayed quiet.
However, when Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه investigated the matter
he came to the decision and the verdict that Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) is innocent
and that he should carry on in his post
and he told Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه I'm not going to sheath a sword that was drawn out by Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Therefore, we would come to the conclusion as many of the historians of Ahlus Sunnah Wal-Jama'ah(أهل السنة والجماعة)
that there was some misunderstanding that happened.
However, Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه investigated the matter
and came to the conclusion that whatever happened
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) should not be held responsible for it
and he should continue and carry on in his position.
And that Malik Bin Nuwairah(مالك بن نويرة) was a man, who was playing
going back and forth, oscillating and he paid the price for his indecisiveness,
in and out of Islam according to the winds of change.
If it appears to be that the Muslims are riding the tide, he becomes a Muslim.
If, whenever they go away, he joins in hands with Al-Murtaddeen(ألمرتدين).
And he ended up paying the price for that with his life.
So Malik Bin Nuwairah(مالك بن نويرة) would be considered as a Murtadd(مُرتَدّ),
because the marriage of Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) to his wife, carried on
and that could only take place if we would consider him a Murtadd(مُرتَد).
I'm mentioning this because this is one of the events that caused the controversy
around the personality of Khalid Ibn Walid رضي الله عنه.
Ibn Taymiyah(اِبْنِ تَيْمِيَّه), he comments on the issue of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and Umar(عُمَر) and
Khalid(خالد) and Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) not particularly this issue, but in general.
He says:
وهكذا أبو بكر ما زال يستعمل خالداً في حرب  أهل الردة،
وفي فتوح العراق و الشام، وبدت منه هفوات كان له فيها تأويل
وقد  ذكر له عنه أنه كان له فيها هوى، فلم يعزله من أجلها بل عاتبه عليها؛
لرجحان  المصلحة على المفسدة في بقائه،
وأن غيره لم يكن يقوم مقامه؛ لأن المتولي الكبير
He says: Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) carried on sending out Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد)
to lead his armies in the most decisive and important battles.
Even though it was reported to Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق),
that Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) has committed some flaws and mistakes
but Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) did not fire him from his post and change him
because the benefit of keeping him was greater than the harm.
And there was nobody who could fulfill the role that Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) was fulfilling.
There's nobody, who can take that position. And then he says:
لأن المتولي الكبير إذا كان خُلُقه يميل إلى اللين فينبغي أن يكون خُلُق نائبه يميل إلى  الشدة
وإذا كان خلقه يميل إلى الشدة فينبغي أن يكون خلق نائبه يميل إلى اللين؛  ليعتدل الأمر
He said: If the Khalifah(خليفه) has a soft personality
then he should appoint a strong person to be his deputy.
While if the Khalifah(خليفه) has, (I don't want to say strong) because Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) was strong
all of them were strong, but was a firm person
then you'd have to have the deputy being a soft mannered person
so that you will have in the end Ietidaal(إعتدال), you'd have a middle way
so he says because Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه had that flexible and lenient personality,
he appointed Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد)
and Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was his deputy
and Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) was the leader of his armies.
But when Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) became Khalifah(خليفه) because of his strong personality.
He changed Khalid(خالد) and he put Abu Obaidah Bin Jarrah(أبوعبيدةبن جراح)
who was a very soft man to lead his armies.
And then Ibn Taymiyah(اِبْنِ تَيْمِيَّه) says
and that makes them fulfilled the role of the Khalifah(خليفه) of the Messenger of Allah
because the Messenger of Allah Himself represented the middle way.
Because Rasool Allah ﷺ represented the middle way
he had two deputies Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and Umar(عُمَر).
One represents one side while the other person represents the opposite side.
But now since Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and Umar(عُمَر) have different character
they have to appoint somebody, who represents the opposite
so that they would be similar, the two together combined could be similar to the middle way of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
ليكون أمره معتدلاً ويكون بذالك من خلفاء الرسول صلى الله عليه وسلم
الذي هو معتدل حتى قال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم انا نبي الرحمه انا نبي الملحمه
Rasool Allah ﷺ he himself represents both sides
because Rasool Allah ﷺ said: I am the Prophet of mercy, I am the Prophet of war.
Rasool Ullah said about himself I am the Prophet of mercy
انا نبي الرحمه وانا نبي الملحمه
And I'm the prophet of war, so Rasool Allah ﷺ represents both sides.
In the Riddah(ردَّة) of Bahrain(بحرين), we know Bahrain(بحرين) today to be the small island in the Persian sea.
But Bahrain(بحرين) in the time of Rasool Allah ﷺ
used to include Island and other islands of the Persian Sea alongside the eastern coast of Saudi Arabia,
UAE, Qatar, all of that would be called Bahrain(بحرين).
So the entire area was called Bahrain(بحرين) in the time of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So we'll talk about events that are happening in Bahrain(بحرين).
It includes all of that area Eastern Saudi Arabia and the Gulf states.
Abul Aalaa Al-Hadhrami(أبوالأعلى ألحضرمي) was the head of the Armies fighting the Murtaddeen(مرتدين) in the area of Al-Bahrain(ألبحربن).
A few important events that happened with Abul Aalaa Al-Hadhrami(أبوالأعلى ألحضرمي).
When they set base and chose a camp, something happened, the camels ran away
with the luggage of the soldiers.
And camels have a habit of being aggressive sometimes and untamed
so the camels just ran away.
So now the soldiers are left behind without their transport and without their luggage in the middle of nowhere in the desert
and there's no water around it's late at night and they're worried.
What can we do?
Abul Aalaa Al-Hadhrami(أبوالأعلى ألحضرمي) says;
Aren't you Muslims?
Aren't you fighting in the sake of Allah?
Come together and let's ask Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ let's make Dua(دُعَا).
So he gathered them all and they started making Dua(دُعَا). On and on and on...
And it was the time of Fajr(فجر).
He said: And we started seeing the clouds coming towards our direction and then it poured rain over us
and water started together in pools.
So we drank from that water and then all of our camels came back to drink from that water
and we got our camels back and our luggage and we had water to drink.
Karamah(كرامة) that happened with Abul Aalaa Al-Hadhrami(أبوالأعلى ألحضرمي), this is one.
Then there's a second Karamah(كرامة) but before that, they attack the enemy.
Actually they attacked the enemy and then pursued them but
they camped next to the enemy at night.
And then Abul Aalaa(أبوالأعلى) was hearing some loud noise coming from the camp of the enemy.
So he told some of his soldiers to go and spy on them and see what's happening.
So they went and found out that these people are drinking, singing
and that they're so drunk they don't know what they're saying.
Abul Aalaa(أبوالأعلى) said: Get ready! And lets attack them now, middle of the night.
They made their move attacked them, and they were just massacring this army
and they are drunk they don't know what's going on.
One of their leaders, Al-Hutam(ألحتم) was asleep.
He wakes up to find that they're under attack,
so he jumps on his horse but the stirrup, where you put your foot falls down or was torn out.
So he is saying;
من يصلح لي رقابي
Who will fix for me, my stirrup.
So one Muslim, who is around he said: I would do that for you,
lift up your leg.
So he lifted up his leg, he chopped off his leg, and just walked away.
So Al-Hutam(ألحتم) just fell down and he told him finished me off.
He said: I won't.
And Al-Hutam(ألحتم) was lying down with his entire leg amputated.
And whenever a Muslim would pass by, he would ask them to finish him off
because he's bleeding he's gonna die anyway.
And whenever one of the soldiers would pass by him, they would say: No!
And they would just leave him there, bleeding.
Until in the end, one of the Ansaar(أنْصَار), Qais Bin Thabit(قيس بن ثابت), or Thabit Bin Qais(ثابت بن قيس), he comes,
so he tells him
أنا الْحتم
Finish me off.
So when he knew that, he is one of the leaders. He said;
I will do that.
And he finished him off but then he said: When I saw his leg laying beside him.
I said: I wish that I didn't kill him, I wish that I'd have left him to bleed to death.
So there was some harshness in the way they will treat Al-Murtaddeen(ألمرتدين)
because of the significance of the crime.
Because we know that Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
إذا قتلتم فَأحسن القِتْله
Even when you kill, you should do it in the most compassionate way.
But the Sahabah(صحابه) saw that with Ar-Riddah(ردَّة), it's an exceptionally great sin.
Therefore, there's a different way to deal with it.
So the enemy retreated and went into this island, and they regrouped, Darin(دارٍ).
So now, Abul Aalaa Al-Hadhrami(أبوالأعلى ألحضرمي) has to cross over a part of the sea,
Allah Alam(الله أعلم) how far but quite a significant distance.
They say: It takes boats an entire day to cross.
So he has to cross this water passageway, and the Muslims have no boats whatsoever.
Plus, I mean, with most of the Sahabah(صحابه) they maybe never ever, were in the boat
and they have to pursue the enemy.
And this is another Karamah(كرامة) that was mentioned by Ibn Kathir(اِبْنِ كَثِيْر) and At-Tabri(ألطبري).
Abul Aalaa Al-Hadhrami(أبوالأعلى ألحضرمي) says:
Let's pray to Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ, ask Allah to give us protecction
because we are Mujahideen(مجاهدين) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
And he said: Bismillah(بسم الله) and they started to walk over the water.
The narrator of this event said that the water would only get as far as the ankles of our horses.
And we're walking this entire distance with our horses over the water
the ones who are walking, Yani(يعني) are not on horses or camels
and they're just walking they said nothing would become wet except our feet
and we're marching on top of the water, until we reach the enemy, we defeated them.
And then we came back and the whole thing happened within one day.
So one of the soldiers in the army he has this line of poetry, he says;
ألم تر أن الله ذلل بحره
وأنزل بالكفار إحدى الجلائل
دعونا الذي شق البحار فجاءنا
بأعجب من فلق البحار الأوائل
He said: Didn't you see, how Allah humbled His sea for us
and Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ brought down His wrath on His enemy.
We pray to Allah to split the sea for us
but Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ gave us a miracle that didn't happen even to the ones before us.
We pray to Allah to split the sea, the sea didn't even have to split, we just walked over it.
So you can see that during the time of Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه
we talked about two Karamaat(كرامات), that only happened to Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) before.
We talked about the Karamah(كرامة) of Abu Muslim Al-Khaulani(أبومسلم ألخولاني)
when he was burnt in the fire, and it didn't affect him
similar to the miracle that happened to Ibrahim عليه السّلام.
And now Abul Aalaa Al-Hadhrami(أبوالأعلى ألحضرمي)
a Karamah(كرامة) happened to him and his army that only happened to Musa عليه السّلام and Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
So Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has given to followers of Muhammadﷺ miracles similar to those given to the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) of Allah.
Now a word regarding Karamaat(كرامات)
first of all, what is the difference between Mu'jiza(معجزة) and Karamah(كرامة)?
They're the same thing, a supernatural event.
However, when it happens to a Nabi(نَبِي) it is called Mu'jiza(معجزة).
And when it happens to a Wali(ولي), or the Awliya(أولياء) of Allah, it is called Karamah(كرامة).
There's a lot said about Karamaat(كرامات) happening to Awliya(أولياء) of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ
and a lot of books written about it, and there's a lot of exaggeration in it.
We do believe that Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ can support His friends, His Awliya(أولياء)
with supernatural occurrences that is part of our Eeman(ايمان).
We do believe that Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ does that.
However we shouldn't believe in some of the things that don't have strong chains of narration
or where the context is not that of Karamah(كرامة).
Because a lot of, is said about these Karamaat(كرامات) and some strange things like for example
there's this story about one of the Awliya(أولياء), who just scratched his skin
so his followers said: Why are you doing that?
He said: Because of one of my students, has invoked my name in the sea
so I scratched my skin and that saves him.
So, he was gonna drown and because I scratched my skin, he was just saved.
Obviously you can't believe something like this, because we only invoke the name of Allah
we don't invoke the name of anyone besides Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
Now, I will give you a key rule, or a general rule that applies to Karamaat(كرامات).
If somebody claims that the Karamah(كرامة) happened in a context out of the Jihad(جهاد),
then take it with a grain of salt.
Because as far as we know,
most of the Karamaat(كرامات) that happened were in that context, or in a similar context, like the context of persecution
like what happened to Abu Muslim Al-Khawlani(أبومسلم ألخولاني).
Somebody who was persecuted, which is a form of Jihad(جهاد), actually
or in the time of battles and Jihad(جهاد). Why?
Because the Muslims then are at the closest level to Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
They are in a situation, where their attachment to Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ is stronger.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ was asked about the fact that
the Shaheed(شهيد) does not feel the horrors of the Day of Judgment and of Sakaraat-Ul-Moat(سكرات الموت).
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: It is enough that he went through the horrors of seeing the swords shine above his head.
I mean, that in itself is enough of a horror.
So because of what, these men who are struggling, are going through
that is a time when Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ gives them His special divine assistance.
So we find that the angels came down to Rasool Allah ﷺ in the Battle of Badr(بدر)
and we found that many of the Karamaat(كرامات) that happened with the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم were in the context of that.
Even with Rasool Allah ﷺ, when the water came out of his fingers. When was that?
that was in the context of the Battle of Tabook(تبوك).
And when Jabir(جابر) invited Rasool Allah ﷺ to his house, and he told him,
I have some food for you, or whatever he had was a very small goat
and a handful of grain, either wheat or barley.
And he told Rasool Allah ﷺ I'm inviting you, and he whispered in his ear.
He said: O Rasool Ullah I'm inviting you with some of your close Sahabah(صحابه)
and then Rasool Allah ﷺ announces it to everyone.
So Jabir(جابر) goes back home and he tells his wife
what can we do Rasool Allah ﷺ has invited the entire community to come to our house.
She told them: Didn't you tell him privately. He said: Yes! I whispered in his ears.
You know how many people showed up?
About 800.
And they all ate and they had their fill.
And there was still food coming out from the pot.
It was a miracle that happened with Rasool Allah ﷺ
that happened during Ghazwa Al-Khandaq(غزوةالخندق).
And one could go on and on and on, about the miracles that happened in the time of Rasool Allah ﷺ
and the Karamaat(كرامات) that happened with the Sahabah(صحابه) and At-Tabieen(ألتابعين)
and the Mujahideen(مجاهدين) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله) after that.
So this is a key or a general rule that you could use or an acid test to tell whether a Karamah(كرامة) is true or not.
There was one priest from Bahrain(بحرين), Christian, who became Muslim.
They told him: Why did you become Muslim? He said;
خَشِيْتُ عِلَّمْ أَفْعَل أَنْ يَمْسَخَنِيَ الله بِمَا شَهَدْتُّ مِن الايات
He said: I was afraid if I didn't become a Muslim
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ would transform me into something else, Maskh(مسخ), destroy me, punish me.
Because of all of the signs that I've seen with my own eyes
this was an army that was supported by Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
He said: He heard voices of angels above the army of Abul Aala Al-Hadhrami(أبوالأعلى ألحضرمي).
So he said: People who are supported with all of these Ayaat(آيات), with all of these miracles
must be on the true path and he said: I'm afraid that if I don’t become a Muslim
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ will punish me and that's why he became Muslim.
So this is a brief overview of the Riddah(ردَّة) of Bahrain(بحرين).
Now the greatest movement of Riddah(ردَّة) ever and the most dangerous one
was that of Musailimah Al-Kazzab(مسيلمة ألكذاب).
Musailimah Al-Kazzab(مسيلمة ألكذاب), his description was, he was a short figure, fair skin Flat nose.
And he started out very early in studying the fields of sorcery
and having connections with Jin(جن) and even just playing tricks of magic
they say that he used to cut the wing of a bird then, and then attach it again.
And the whole thing was just a trick, an optical illusion.
And he would travel around studying these different arts of deception
and then he started claiming that he's a prophet during the time of Rasool Allah ﷺ
and his situation was becoming dangerous even during the time of Muhammadﷺ.
And he belongs to a strong tribe, they have very fast land, powerful fighters.
So it was a very dangerous movement.
And he dared to send a letter to Muhammadﷺ with two of his followers, he said;
من مسيلمه رسول الله إلى محمد رسول الله
From Musaylimah(مسيلمه) the Messenger of Allah, to Muhammad(محمد) the Messenger of Allah.
The earth is split into two halves, one half belongs to you, and one half belongs to me
but Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) are people, who are transgressing.
He said: You have to give me half of your territory.
فَاِنِّي أشركتُ فى الأمر معك
Because I was given partnership with you from Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ
I'm your partner in Prophethood.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ asked these two men, who are with him
what do you say about Musaylimah(مسيلمه)?
They said: We say what our people say.
That he is the messenger of Allah, Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
لَولا أنَّ الرسُل لا تُقتل لقتلتكما
If it wasn't for the fact that messengers are not killed, I would have killed you
I would have executed you.
But there was an established norm, that you do not harm the carriers of messages.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ sent back a letter,
بِسْمِ اللَّهِ الرَّحْمَنِ الرَّحِيمِ، مِنْ محمد رسول الله إِلَى مُسَيْلِمَةَ الْكَذَّابِ
أَمَّا بَعْدُ، فإِنَّ الْأَرْضَ لِلَّهِ يُورِثُها مَنْ يَشاءُ مِنْ عِبادِهِ وَالْعاقِبَةُ لِلْمُتَّقِينَ
بِسْمِ اللَّهِ الرَّحْمَنِ الرَّحِيمِ،
from Muhammad(محمد) the Messenger of Allah to Musaylimah(مسيلمة) the imposter, the liar.
The earth belongs to Allah and He will inherit it, to whomever He wills
and the end belongs to the righteous.
The earth Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ can make it rotate from one party to another it belongs to Allah,
but the end, the last round belongs to the believers
and he sent it with a Sahabi(صحابي) Al-Ansari(ألأنصاري), Habib Ibn Zaid(حبيب إبن زيد)
one of Al-Ansaar(أنْصَار) and he is the son of Musaibah Bint Ka'ab(مصيبة بنت كعب).
So he carries the letter of Rasool Allah ﷺ and he goes to meet Musaylimah(مسيلمة).
Obviously Musaylimah(مسيلمة) is upset with the response of Muhammadﷺ
belittling him, calling him Musaylimah(مسيلمة) the liar, the imposter.
So Musaylimah(مسيلمة) asks this man, what do you say about Muhammad(محمد)? He says, I say:
أشهد أنَّ محمدًا رسول الله
What do you say about me? He says: I can't hear you.
So Musaylimah(مسيلمة) cuts off part of his body
and he asks him again, same answer so it cuts off another part of the body.
and he keeps on cutting him into pieces, until he fell down dead.
So you can see; how evil Musaylimah(مسيلمة) is, that he didn't even stick to the established norms of not killing the messengers
and you can see that Rasool Allah ﷺ even though he had the right to execute these two men
because of their Riddah(ردَّة), he set them free.
So Habib(حبيب) was a Shaheed(شهيد) in the court of Musailimah Al-Kazzab(مسيلمة ألكذاب).
There is a very important figure within the movement of Riddah(ردَّة)
his name is Ar-Rajal Bin Unfua Al-Hanfi(ألرجال بن عنفُوة ألحنفي).
Ar-Rajal Bin Unfua(ألرجال بن عنفُوة) was part of the delegation that came to meet Rasool Allah ﷺ from Bannu Hanifah(بنوحنيفة).
Bannu Hanifah(بنوحنيفة) just as every other Arab tribe has sent a delegation
paying homage to Rasool Allah ﷺ and giving him Baiyah(بَيْعة) on Islam.
And by the way, Musaylimah(مسيلمة) was a member of this delegation
and he did give Rasool Allah ﷺ Baiyah(بَيْعة) on Islam in one narration.
In another narration, he was actually guarding their belongings and he didn't attend the meeting itself.
But anyway, Bannu Hanifah(بنوحنيفة) were followers of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, Ar-Rajal Bin Unfua(ألرجال بن عنفُوة), he stayed behind
and he was attending the Halaqaat(حلقات) of Rasool Allah ﷺ
and he memorized a significant portion of Qur'an.
So, you can say that he had some Ilm(علم) he had some knowledge
and then Rasool Allah ﷺ sent him back to his people to sway them, to bring them back,
to convince them that what Musaylimah(مسيلمة) is doing is false.
Ar-Rajjal(ألرجال) goes there and he turns around 180 degrees
and he becomes a Murtadd(مُرتَد).
And his Fitnah(فِتْنَه) was worse than the Fitnah(فِتْنَه) of Musaylimah(مسيلمة) himself.
Abu Hurairah رضي الله عنه said that I was once in a gathering with Rasool Allah ﷺ
and Rasool Allah ﷺ said that there is a man among you
whose molar tooth in hellfire is bigger than the mountain of Uhud(أحَد).
There's somebody sitting with us now, when he dies, he is gonna go to Hell fire
and his molar tooth is bigger than the mountain of Uhud(أحَد).
Abu Hurairah(أبوهريرة) said: Everyone in that gathering died, except me
and Ar-Rajal Bin Unfua(ألرجال بن عنفُوة).
And I was very frightened because of that.
Until I saw Ar-Rajjal(ألرجال) claimed that Musaylimah(مسيلمة) is the messenger of Allah.
I knew that the Hadith(حديث) is talking about him
because he was worried the only two remaining were him and Ar-Rajjal(ألرجال) but then Ar-Rajjal(ألرجال) apostated.
Abu Hurairah(أبوهريرة) says about him;
He was more significant in sowing discord among his people
than was Musaylimah(مسيلمة) himself. Why?
Because of his knowledge.
The Fitnah(فِتْنَه) of somebody, who has knowledge or a scholar is greater than any other Fitnah(فِتْنَه)
people know that a disbeliever is a disbeliever
but a Munafiq(منافق), who has knowledge is very dangerous.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ says in a Hadith(حديث) that
the worst thing I fear for my Ummah(امة) is the hypocrite, who has a very nice tongue
somebody who knows to play around with words.
So when the scholar deviates, an entire people deviate with him
and that's why when Imam Ahmad Bin Hambal(إمام أحمد بن حنبل) was told by some of his contemporaries
that in your situation, you're excused you can give in to, what your persecutors want.
He said: If I speak what they want me to say that would mislead all of the people
because they wanted him to say that Qur'an is Makhlooq(مخلوق)
they wanted them to say that Qur'an was created.
He said: If I say that, then the people will go along with me, and he refused.
And that's why the Ahbaar(أحبار) of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل)
in the time of Eesa Ibn Maryam(عيسى إبن مريم), when Eesa عليه السّلام gave them Da'wah(دعوة)
the Ahbaar(أحبار), the scholars of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) when they turned down the Da'wah(دعوة)
the people did not believe in Eesa عليه السّلام.
They said our scholars did not say so, our scholars did not give a fatwa(فتوى) to follow you.
And that's why the people were deceived
and the only people who followed Eesa Ibn Maryam(عيسى إبن مريم)
were some fishermen and youth but the masses remained behind their deviant scholars.
So it's important to follow the scholars of Haqq(حق)
because it's not just the knowledge that the person possesses.
That is a standard of how close they are to Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ
Iblees(إبليس) was very scholarly.
And we know of many stories of like Balaam(بلعام) from Bannu Israel(بنواسرائيل) and others, who were very scholarly,
but they refused to accept the truth.
In the time of Musa عليه السّلام when he left his people in the hands of Haroon(هارون)
because Samri(سامري) was a very charismatic figure
and he knew how to speak well he deceived the people
and he pulled the rug from under Haroon عليه السّلام, who was a Nabi(نَبِي) of Allah.
And he took charge over the people and the people left Haroon عليه السّلام and they followed him.
So it's not always how popular a person is
if you would run Haroon عليه السّلام and As-Samri(ألسامري) in a fair and free elections
As-Samri(ألسامري) is gonna win.
So that's not the criteria of how good a person is.
As-Samri(ألسامري) was deviant and the people followed him, and they left Haroon عليه السّلام. Why?
Because As-Samri(ألسامري), he knew how to fool the people
and he was a very charismatic figure, himself.
So Ar-Rajjal(ألرجال) was a great Fitnah(فِتْنَه)
and in the Battle of Al-Yamamah(أليمامة), Musaylima(مسيلمة) appointed pointed two men
on his right and left flanks, Ar-Rajjal(ألرجال) was one of them
and Mahakkam(محكم) was the second.
Musailimah Al-Kazzab(مسيلمة ألكذاب), even though he was a very bright figure.
When he tried to imitate Qur'an he came up with funny things
and that's Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله),
you know, a person can be very eloquent
but when they try to imitate Qur'an they come up with foolish talk.
He would say, O frog, Croak as you Croak
the bottom of you is in dirt and the top of you is in water.
He would describe this desert rat that has big ears.
He says all of us just head and ears.
Did I mentioned to you about the harvesting Surah(سورة) that he has?
He says: Planting seeds and then the seeds grow and you harvest the grain
and then you crush it and you make bread out of it and you mix the bread with soup.
والزارعات زرعا،  والمُبذرات زرعًا، والحاصدات حصدًا، والعاجنات عجنًا،
And then he says eat from the Sareed(سريد), the soup with the bread.
Somebody who was listening to this so called Surah(سورة), he said:
O Musaylimah(مسيلمة) I'm not really sure whether your angel is descending
on your heart or on your stomach, it's all about food.
And when he heard that Rasool Allah ﷺ was given Al-Kausar(كوثر)
إِنَّا أَعْطَيْنَاكَ الْكَوْثَرَ
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has given Rasool Allah ﷺ Al-Kausar(كوثر), which is a river in Jannah(جنة).
So they told Musaylimah(مسيلمة)
because Musaylimah(مسيلمة) would always try to imitate Rasool Allah ﷺ
because of jealousy, they would tell him,
Rasool Allah ﷺ was given Al-Kausar(كوثر), what were you given? He said:
إنا اعطيناك المفتاح فصلي لربك وارتاح
We have given you the key so pray and rest, he has the key Jannah(جنة).
It is reported that Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) met him
when Amr Bin Al-Aas رضي الله عنه was a Mushrik(مشرك).
And Amr(عمرو) told him Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has revealed to Muhammadﷺ a Surah(سورة) called Surah Al-Asr(سورة العصر).
So Musaylimah(مسيلمة) said and same thing with me, Allah has given me a Surah(سورة)
يا وَبْر يا وَبْر، إنما أنت أذنان وصَدْر، وسائرك حفز نَقْز
Some of his nonsense. So, Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) said;
والله إنك لتعلم أني أعلم أنك تكذب
In the name of Allah, you know that I know that you're a liar.
Ibn Kathir(اِبْنِ كَثِيْر), he comments on this and he says
that the words of Musaylimah(مسيلمة) were so foolish that even a Mushrik(مشرك), a non Muslim realize that his nonsense
and when Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه after the whole fiasco ended
and when he met the delegation of Bannu Hanifa(بنوحنيفه), who came again to give him Baiyah(بَيْعة),
he said: Can you please tell me some of his Qur'an?
So they said: O Khalifah(خليفه), please excuse us, they know how foolish it was.
He said: No! I insist on you, to tell me some of the Qur'an of Musaylima(مسيلمة).
So they went ahead, and he said: How could any mind buy into something like this?
To tell you how come they would fall into something like this?
Two reasons, for some people it's like this old man, who came and said,
I want to meet Musaylima(مسيلمة), they said: Woe to you say, Musaylima(مسيلمة) Rasool Ullah.
He said: I'm not gonna say that he's Rasool Ullah, until I meet him.
So he goes into meet Musaylima(مسيلمة), and he tells him to narrate some of his Qur'an.
And then the old man says: I know that you are a liar.
But a liar from my tribe is better for me than a true man from Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
You are from my tribe, I would rather follow you, then follow Rasool Allah ﷺ
even though that I know that you're a liar and that Muhammadﷺ is telling the truth.
With some other people, it goes back to what Abu Bakr Al-Baqalani(ابوبكرألباقلاني) said;
one of the scholars, he said;
فأما كلام مسيلمة الكذاب وما زعم أنه قرآن فهو أخس من أن ننشغل به وأسخف من أن نفكر فيه
He said: It's so foolish, it doesn't even deserve one to think about it.
وإنما نقلنا منه طرفًا ليتعجب القارئ وليتبصر الناظر
And we only mentioned it to amaze and surprise the reader
فإنه على سخافته قد أضل، وعلى ركاكته قد أزل، وميدان الجهل واسع
And he said: Even though it is so foolish nevertheless, it's still deceived many people
and that's because the field of ignorance is wide.
وكل صاقة كعقدة
For everything that falls down, there will be somebody who will pick it up.
There are going to be people out there, who are going to buy into any cult
whatever idea you throw out there are going to be some people who would buy into it.
Now, not all of Bannu Hanifa(بنوحنيفه) followed Musaylima(مسيلمة).
There were some steadfast among them, like Thumamah Bin Uthaal(ثمامة بن أثال)
he was one of their noble leaders, and he went to his people and he told them
that there is no partnership in Prophethood there's only one prophet
and that's Muhammadﷺ and this man is lying believe and follow me.
Because I am going to go to Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) and ask him to give me peace.
And he went to Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) and Khalid(خالد) granted him peace
and granted his people peace.
And Thumamah(ثمامة) was instrumental in fighting against Al-Murtaddeen(ألمرتدين).
So there were some people from Bannu Hanifa(بنوحنيفه), who did not follow Musailimah Al-Kazzab(مسيلمة ألكذاب)
among every people, you have good and bad.
So, Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) was given instructions to attack Musailimah Al-Kazzab(مسيلمة ألكذاب)
and he was appointed leader among the Muslim armies.
He was entrusted with this very critical event in the time of Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق).
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) was so concerned about what was happening in Al-Yamamah(أليمامة)
that he would go out in the morning waiting for the careers to bring in letters from the combat zone.
Because it was the most dangerous event ever, on Khilafah Al-Islamiya(خِلَافَة ألأإسلامية).
Now, there was a group of about 50 or 60 men from Bannu Hanifa(بنوحنيفه) followers of Musaylimah(مسيلمة),
who went out to raid another tribe because there was a problem between them
and they were sleeping at night and they didn't know that
they're very close to the camp grounds of Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) and his army.
So the Muslims succeeded in capturing all of them 50 or 60 men.
So, Khalid(خالد) thought that these were spies.
They said: We're not spies.
We just had this issue with another tribe and we raided them
and we didn't know that you were around and they were telling the truth
Khalid Ibn Walid رضي الله عنه knowing that they are followers of Musaylimah(مسيلمة)
ordered the execution of the entire group, 60 men.
The head was Maj'ah(مجاع), he was very respected among his people. So they said;
If you're going to execute us all, spare this man, spare Maj'ah(مجاع),
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) agreed.
He executed all of them and he spared Maj'jah(مجاعة)
and he held him as a hostage with him and he entrusted him to his wife.
The wife of Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد), the former wife, the ex wife of Malik Bin Nuwaira(مالك بن نويرة) - Umm Tamim(أم تميم).
She was the one, who was entrusted with him obviously, he's in chain.
And this was a setback because he was a very prominent leader among Banu Hanifa(بنوحنيفة).
So this was one event that happened before the actual battle, itself.
So now, Banu Hanifa(بنوحنيفة) mobilized all of their forces
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) mobilize forces,
and they were meeting in this field in Al-Yamamah(أليمامة) and the battle started.
In the first wave of attack, the enemy was so strong in his blow
that it entirely took the Muslims by surprise and push them back.
The wave of attack was so powerful that the A'raab(أعراب), the nomads and the new Muslims
could not withstand it, and they retreated.
So now the core group of Sahabah رضي الله عنهم, Al-Muhajiroon(ألمهاجرون) wal-Ansaar(والأنْصَار), are now surrounded
so they had to retreat.
They retreated so much that the spearhead of the enemy
was able to make it to the tent of Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) - himself.
Now he wasn't there the tents are set behind the rear of the army.
So the army had to retreat so far, that now the front or the spearhead of the army of Banu Hanifa(بنوحنيفة)
was able to make it to the actual tent of Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد)
and they came in, and they were about to kill Umm Tamim(أم تميم)
but Maj'jah(مجَّاعة), who was tied up in the tent, he gave her protection and he said;
This is a great noble woman, Don't touch her.
So it was Maj'jah(مجَّاعة), who protected the wife of Khalid Ibn Walid رضي الله عنه.
Obviously then the Muslims had to regroup.
Al-Muhajiroon(ألمهاجرون) wal-Ansaar(والأنْصَار), they went to Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) and said;
يا خالد أخلصنا
O Khalid(خالد) separate us.
What they meant was?
Do not mix us together in this army
have the Muhajiroon(ألمهاجرون) wal-Ansaar(والأنْصَار) under their own banner.
And these new Muslims and the Bedouins, nomads have them under their own banner
so that we know where we're attacked from.
Because in that initial blow it was the nomads, who retreated and that has caused the entire Muslim army, a setback.
So, now they're saying;
يا خالد أخلصنا
Separator us.
So, Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) said;
O people organized separately, so that we may know the valor of each clan
and know from where we are approached by the enemy.
Because now there was a blame going on.
Al Muhajiroon(ألمهاجرون) wal-Ansaar(والأنْصَار) told the nomads it's because of you this happened
and the nomads said: No! You settlers don't know, how to fight.?
So they said: Fine, let's all separate under our own banners
so that it will become clear, where we were approached from?
So, now, among A'raab(أعراب) each tribe would be set under their own banners
so you'd know that these are Banu Fulan(بنوفلان).
this is a tribe of so and so, this is a clan of so and so.
And Al-Muhajiroon(ألمهاجرون) were separate and Al-Ansaar(ألأنْصَار) were separate.
The leadership of Al-Muhajiroon(ألمهاجرون) was given to Salim Mola Abu Hudaifah(سالم مولا أبوحذيفة)
and the banner of Al-Ansaar(ألأنْصَار) was given to Thabit Bin Qais(ثابت بن قيس)
Thabit Bin Qais(ثابت بن قيس) is carrying the banner of Ansaar(أنْصَار).
And now it's going to be shame for any battalion to be defeated.
So they have to show their steadfastness.
So what Thabit(ثابت) did
he made for himself a hole in the ground that buried him, a knee high.
So, that he cannot retreat even if he wanted to
and he held the banner and he fought, until he was killed.
Salim(سالم), who was a servant and this shows you equality in Islam.
Among Al-Muhajireen(مهاجرين), you've people from every different tribe and groups
but they have given their banner to Salim(سالم) who was a slave. Why?
Because he was Hamil-Al Qur'an(حاما ألقرآن) because he was a memorizer of Qur'an
and he said: I know why you give me the banner?
It's because of the Qur'an.
And he said:
بِئس حامل القرآن أنا أن أوتيتم من قِبَلِ
He said: I'm the worst carrier of Qur'an, if you will be approached from my side.
It's not appropriate for somebody, who's carrying Qur'an to do something against Qur'an.
Qur'an is not just memorizing it, in your heart, Qur'an is applying it to your life.
That's the understanding of the Sahabah(صحابه).
If you are memorizing Qur'an, you have to live up to a certain standard
because you have Qur'an in your chest, you have to follow what you know.
Practice what you preach and walk the talk.
Not just memorize it, so that Qur'an can be Hujjah Alaik(حجة عليك) on the day of judgment
it can be evidence against you on the Day of Judgment.
So Salim(سالم) carried the banner and he fought and the Muhajireen(مهاجرين) were firm
and the Ansaar(أنْصَار) were firm.
But Banu Hanifa(بنوحنيفة) were putting up a stiff resistance
and the attack was going on in waves.
A wave would attack and then they would go back and another wave would come
and those waves were going both ways
The Muslims were sending out waves and the Mushrikeen(مُشركين) were sending out waves.
And the Muslims had to encourage each other
and they would have speakers stand up and give Mu'aza(مؤعظة)
and give a Khut'ba(خطبة) to encourage others to fight.
So Zaid Ibn Al-Khattab(زيد إبن الخطاب), the brother of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب), he told
his followers grit your teeth, meaning press your nerves very hard and just attack
go straight ahead, grit your teeth people and Strike your enemy and proceed straight ahead.
And they made a very powerful and violent blow to the enemy
and Ar-Rajjal(ألرجال) was killed,
Ar-Rajjal(ألرجال) the second in command after Musailimah Al-Kazzab(مسيلمة ألكذاب) was killed.
And the one, who killed him was Zaid Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه.
Abdur Rahman Ibn Abi Bakr(عبدالرحمن إبن أبي بكر) he saw Al-Muhakkam(ألمحكم)
which is also the head of the other flank of the army of Musaylimah(مسيلمة)
you had Ar-Rajjal(ألرجال) and Al-Muhakkam(ألمحكم) they were the right and left flank.
So Abdur Rahman Ibn Abi Bakr(عبدالرحمن إبن أبي بكر) spoted Al-Muhakkam(ألمحكم)
giving a speech to his people encouraging them to fight.
And I mentioned to you that Abdur Rahman(عبدالرحمن) was a very good Archer.
So he was able to strike Al-Muhakkam(ألمحكم) right in his throat,
while he was standing and giving a speech and he dropped him dead.
So now you have Ar-Rajjal(ألرجال) and Al-Muhakkam(ألمحكم) are both dead
but still Banu Hanifa(بنوحنيفة) were fighting.